ACTWU Publications 5619 PUBS
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ACTWU Publications
1917-1998
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union (ACTWU)
Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America (ACWA)
5619 PUBS
9.17 cubic feet
9.2 linear ft.
Publications.
6849656
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, April 13, 2015
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 21, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes.
Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals.
Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants.
Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management.
Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable.
During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Biographical / Historical
The Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the most significant union representing workers in the men's clothing industry, was founded in New York City in 1914 as a breakaway movement from the United Garment Workers. Radical and immigrant workers in the tailors' and cutters' locals were the core of the seceding group, which advocated industrial unionism and economic strikes in opposition to the UGW's craft organization, which they saw as conservative and timid. Their diverging views had come to the fore during the historic 1910 dispute at the Chicago firm Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. The opposition called the strike against the UGW leadership's advice, and reached a path-breaking agreement with management that established an arbitration system to settle disputes. Members flocked to the new union. Around 50,000 strong at its founding, by 1920 the ACWA counted about 170,000 members. Initially composed mostly of immigrants of Jewish European descent with Socialist leanings, the ACWA quickly welcomed members of a great number of nationalities and diverse backgrounds. Like in other garment unions, most workers and many members were women, but the leadership was predominantly male, a situation that did not change for many decades. Early on the union adopted a centralized administrative structure combined with industrial unionism, with the joint boards' by-laws having precedence over those of locals. Espousing a philosophy perhaps brought over by its early immigrant socialist members, the Amalgamated went beyond bread and butter issues and adopted a distinctive form of social unionism that was largely absent in the American labor movement. Starting in the 1920s, it provided educational opportunities and recreational facilities for its members, as well as services such as an insurance plan, banks offering personal loans at low interest rates, low-cost housing cooperatives, medical clinics, and even union-owned restaurants. Sidney Hillman was the first president of the new union and the most important officer in its history. He applied his experience as bargaining representative in Chicago to the whole industry. Under his leadership the union made significant strides in securing better wages and working conditions for its members, and at the same time it consolidated gains and provided stability to the industry through the widespread adoption of the arbitration system tested at Hart, Schaffner, and Marx. Hillman paid close attention to industry issues, such as production, pricing, and marketing. In order to help management meet the competition of non-union firms, the union conducted studies of efficiency, work methods, and factory costs. Letters to the official publication of the union, Advance, document the controversy that ensued within the union over what was perceived to be collaboration with management. Hillman also understood the importance of labor's involvement in national affairs and political action. In the 1920s the ACWA sent delegates to the Conference for Progressive Political Action and to the Farmer-labor party conventions. Although many members and officers were Socialists, the union stopped short of officially endorsing the party. Communist attempts at gaining influence within the union were firmly curbed. Hillman's participation in national affairs and politics became prominent during the New Deal, when he became a close advisor to Franklin D. Roosevelt on labor and economic issues. He also served on the board of the National Recovery Administration. Later, during World War II, he helped establish the Labor's Non Partisan League. He was also named associate director of the Office of Production Management, which assisted in mobilizing the nation's resources for the war effort. Hillman's prestige perhaps reflected the healthy condition of his union, which by the end of the conflict was strong and stable. During the post World War II period the union faced a number of significant challenges. Membership continued to grow (peaking at 395,000 in 1968), but the union's political influence and visibility in national affairs declined. In their never ending pursuit of lower production costs, many firms relocated to the South, forcing the union to engage in large organizing efforts. Simultaneously, signs began to appear of changes that would lead to the almost complete demise of the domestic apparel industry and, ultimately, to the erosion of union membership. Foreign imports of cheap clothing goods steadily grew in the 1950s and 1960s, and mushroomed in the following two decades, plunging employment in the apparel sector into a steady decline. Union efforts to stem the tide included Buy American campaigns and extensive lobbying in Congress, but they were to no avail. In 1976, the ACWA merged with the Textile Workers of America to become the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Despite successful and much publicized nationwide actions such as the Farah boycott and the J.P. Stevens corporate campaign, the woes threatening the union's existence continued unabated. The fate of the domestic industry was sealed in the late 1970s and the 1980s by the flight of firms chasing tax breaks and cheap labor abroad. By 1995, when ACTWU voted to merge with the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, their combined membership was 350,000. The new Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE!) seemed poised to infuse new life in a troubled union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5619: ACWA Records 5619 AV: ACTWU Audio-Visual Materials 5619 C-S MB: ACTWU President Jack Sheinkman Additional Books, Memorabilia, and Files 5619 F: ACTWU Motion Picture Films 5619 G: ACTWU Graphics 5619 MB: ACTWU Memorabilia Collection 5619 mf: ACWA Records Parts 1-3 on Microfilm 5619 OH: ACWA Oral History Project Records 5619 P: ACTWU Photographs 5619/001: ACTWU Collective Bargaining Agreements 5619/002: ACWA Education Department Records 5619/003: ACWA Sidney Hillman Scrapbooks 5619/004: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Files 5619/004 fiche: ACTWU President Jacob Sheinkman Speeches on Microfiche 5619/005: ACWA Bessie Hillman Papers 5619/006: ACTWU Executive Vice-President's Office Files 5619/007: ACTWU Organizing Department Files 5619/008: ACWA Rieve-Pollock Foundation Files 5619/009: ACTWU Operations Department Sidney Hillman Awards Files 5619/010: ACWA Jacob Potofsky files 5619/011: ACTWU Southern Regional Joint Board Files 5619/012: ACTWU Company Files 5619/013: ACTWU Research Department Correspondence Chronological Files 5619/014: ACWA Local 169 Files 5619/015: ACTWU Department of Occupational Safety and Health Files
Textile workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Clothing workers--Labor unions--New York (State); Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees; UNITE HERE (Organization)
6849656
- Box: 1, Folder: 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: 50th Anniversary of the Textile Workers Union of America, Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    By TWUA (Textile Workers Union of America). Commemorative Brochure. Philadelphia, PA, September 7, 1989. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 2, Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: The 340 Leader, Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    By Retail Clothing Salesmen's Union, Local 340. v.15:no.3 (1976:Sep./Oct.). Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 3, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: ACTWU and Civil Rights, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Item is in English.
  - Item 2: ACTWU and Civil Rights, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 2. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 4, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: ACTWU-PAC: Big Business. Corporate Lobbyists. Special Interests., Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 2: ACTWU-PAC: Big Business. Corporate Lobbyists. Special Interests., Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 3: ACTWU-PAC: Big Business. Corporate Lobbyists. Special Interests., Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 3. Item is in English.
  - Item 4: ACTWU-PAC: Las Grandes Corporaciones, Las Grandes Influencias, y Los Intereses Creados, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Item is in Spanish.
  - Item 5: ACTWU-PAC: Las Grandes Corporaciones, Las Grandes Influencias, y Los Intereses Creados, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 2. Item is in Spanish.
  - Item 6: ACTWU-PAC: Las Grandes Corporaciones, Las Grandes Influencias, y Los Intereses Creados, Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 3. Item is in Spanish.
- Box: 1, Folder: 5, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: ACTWU Songbook, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 2: ACTWU Songbook, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 3: ACTWU Songbook, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Box: 1, Folder: 6, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Affirmative Action for the Disabled: A How To Manual for Labor Unions, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    By Joyce D. Miller; Robert Enteen; Roger Herman; Madeleine Tramm. Item is in English.
  - Item 2: Affirmative Action for the Disabled: A How To Manual for Labor Unions, Publication (Box 1, Folder 6)
    By Joyce D. Miller; Robert Enteen; Roger Herman; Madeleine Tramm. Copy 2. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 7, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: AHAP: Amalgamated Health Assistance Program, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Item is in English;Spanish.
  - Item 2: AHAP: Amalgamated Health Assistance Program, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 2. Item is in English;Spanish.
  - Item 3: AHAP: Amalgamated Health Assistance Program, Publication (Box 1, Folder 7)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 3. Item is in English;Spanish.
- Box: 1, Folder: 8, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Apparel and Textile Topics for the 90s': Moving Towards a Safer and More Productive Workplace, Publication (Box 1, Folder 8)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). April 29-30, 1992. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 9, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Aqui Teine Lo Que Debe Saber El Miembro, Publication (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Box: 1, Folder: 10, Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: Art: Susan Rotolo, Publication (Box 1, Folder 10)
    By Susan Rotolo. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 11, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Item 1: Bienvenido a la Union, Publication (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Box: 1, Folder: 12, Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Item 1: Chemical Hazards, Publication (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Box: 1, Folder: 13, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 1: Civil Rights Act of 1991, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 2: Civil Rights Act of 1991, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Item 3: Civil Rights Act of 1991, Publication (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Box: 1, Folder: 14, Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Item 1: A Commitment to Progress: The Dream Continues, ACTWU 1972-1987, Publication (Box 1, Folder 14)
    By Burt Beck. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 15, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Item 1: Como Funciona la Union, Publication (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Box: 1, Folder: 16, Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Item 1: Conducting Your Union Meeting, Publication (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Box: 1, Folder: 17, Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Item 1: Congressional Report Card, Publication (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Box: 1, Folder: 18, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Item 1: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Item 2: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Box: 1, Folder: 19, Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Item 1: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Item is in French.
  - Item 2: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Box: 1, Folder: 20, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Item 1: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Item 2: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Item 3: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Item 4: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Item 5: Constitution, Publication (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Box: 1, Folder: 21, Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Item 1: The Constitution of the United States of America, Publication (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 22, Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Item 1: Contract Provisions for the Disabled, Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Item 2: Contract Provisions for the Disabled, Publication (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Box: 1, Folder: 23, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Item 1: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 7, 1993. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 2: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 7, 1993. Copy 2. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 3: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 8, 1993. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 4: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 8, 1993. Copy 2. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 5: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 9, 1993. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 6: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 9, 1993. Copy 2. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 7: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 10, 1993. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
  - Item 8: Contract Unity, Publication (Box 1, Folder 23)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). ACTWU 6th Constitutional Convention, Las Vegas, NV, June 10, 1993. Copy 2. Item is in English;Spanish;French.
- Box: 1, Folder: 24, Publication (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Item 1: Danger and Dyeing: The Cancer Threat From Benzidine-Type Dyes, Publication (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Item 2: Danger and Dyeing: The Cancer Threat From Benzidine-Type Dyes, Publication (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Box: 1, Folder: 25, Publication (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Item 1: Delegate's Guide, Publication (Box 1, Folder 25)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Fourth Contistitutional Convention, Miami Beach, FL, June 15-19, 1987. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 26, Publication (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Item 1: Delegate's Guide, Publication (Box 1, Folder 26)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Special Convention, Miami Beach, FL, June, 1995. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 27, Publication (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Item 1: Does ACTWU Really Work, Publication (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Box: 1, Folder: 28, Publication (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Item 1: Ergo-What? Ergonomics!, Publication (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Box: 1, Folder: 29, Publication (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Item 1: Ever Forward: Forty Years of Progress, Publication (Box 1, Folder 29)
    By Vera Miller. A Short History of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. Item is in English.
- Box: 1, Folder: 30, Publication (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Item 1: Fire! What Should We Do?, Publication (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Box: 1, Folder: 31, Publication (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Item 1: Health and Safety: Local Union Action Manual, Publication (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Box: 1, Folder: 32, Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Item 1: Health Care for All, Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Item 2: Health Care for All, Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Item 3: Health Care for All, Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Item is in Chinese.
  - Item 4: Health Care for All, Publication (Box 1, Folder 32)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Copy 2. Item is in Chinese.
- Box: 1, Folder: 33, Publication (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Item 1: Holiday Greetings, Publication (Box 1, Folder 33)
    By ACTWU (Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers' Union). Many languages on cover. Item is in English;Spanish.
- Box: 1, Folder: 34, Publication (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Item 1: How ACTWU Works, Publication (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Box: 1, Folder: 35, Publication (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Item 1: How the Union Works, Publication (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Item 2: How the Union Works, Publication (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Item 3: How the Union Works, Publication (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Box: 1, Folder: 36, Publication (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Item 1: The Inheritance, Publication (Box 1, Folder 36)